e
e e
are you ready
this we're ready I think we'll get
started it's exactly
3:30 hello good good afternoon I think
we're going to get started it's exactly
3:30 welcome to the uh January 14th
traffic commission meeting um this is
the first meeting of year 2025 and I
want to be able to get us started a
slightly different way than we've have
in the past I want to make sure that we
introduce each of ourselves because
there's a new member and there's about
to be a
transition um so we want to be able to
make sure that people are aware of the
next of the next member so I'm going to
start by saying I I'm Steve Campbell I'm
the director of Public Works and the
chair of the of the traffic commission
I'm going to start in this direction and
then we'll go in in this direction so
Cindy good afternoon uh Cindy McCormack
I'm a deputy director in the Department
of Public Works um so and the city
engineer city
engineer good afternoon I'm Lauren Finn
I'm a senior planner here at the
city and then let's start at that at
your end
Mindy hi I'm Mindy Gable I am
administrative assistant and traffic
commission
administrator Sergeant Michael jeras
Patrol Services Sergeant Langster City
bureau of police and you're going to be
making a change this is your last your
last meeting with the traffic commission
for us it is and you'll be and the
gentleman who'll be taking your place is
Sergeant dorsy
Samra very good so you'll be introduced
to him at the next traffic commission
meeting two months from now and he'll be
fulfilling this role Dino yeah Dino
mandros uh City
representative very good and the latest
new city repres representative is my
name is Philip stump Kennedy I go by
Phil um I live in southeast should I say
more about this if you w if you wish to
please uh I'm originally from Hershey
and uh I'm excited to be here so we're
we're we're very ha glad that we're
doing this rotation Dino has consented
to be able to stay on
for an undetermined future and there was
a vacancy and we're very happy to have
Philip on board uh last member of the
committee is of the commission is
council member Janet Diaz who will be
about a half an hour late to this
meeting this
afternoon so I'm calling I've called the
I unofficially called the meeting to
order at
3:30 um the first the first item of
business is the minutes of the previous
meeting minutes of the November 2024
meeting make a motion to approve the
minutes second there's been a motion and
a second second Is there further
conversation if not all in favor say I I
I any
opposed thank you so the minutes have
been approved the next part of our
agenda is uh staff project
updates Cindy may I turn it over to you
sure um yes we just wanted to be able to
provide some updates about um some of
the projects that we're working on in
the city um around uh roadway
improvements and those kind of things
also provide an update on the RPP we are
currently um with the residential permit
parking we have been approved to Pilot
um a program um basically we're looking
at two different areas within the city
to Pilot um evaluating how we Implement
RPP and potentially expanding some of
the areas that currently exist we've
been doing some data collection um
trying to work through some of our GIS
tools to automate the process knowing
that this could this will be a process
that we'll need to be implementing at a
larger scale in the future um so we've
been working through some of that um we
are also working with uh the Lancaster
parking authority on um some license
plate readers so that we can collect
data such as occupancy data related to
the parking um so we're continuing to
work through that we anticipate you know
that we will be um trying to finalize
some of these areas in the coming months
um and we still need to identify we'll
be reaching out to Residents in those
areas that are impacted to have public
meetings and have more discussion about
that so are there
any I can provide updates then on some
of the projects if that's if everyone's
good with the RPP
we we seem to be fine with that okay go
with the projects so um at the staff
level we recognize that maybe um the
public isn't always aware of all the
projects that we're working on um within
you know the um RightWay division so we
just wanted to provide sort of an update
um to the traffic commission and provide
a public forum so that most people are
aware of what we're working on um we've
created this list which I won't go
through in detail for everything but
this list identifies uh the projects
that we're currently working on within
the um division so we have a couple
projects that we're planning on uh
taking to construction this year um Duke
Street is um the South Duke Street
corridor from church to Chesapeake is
one of the main uh projects that we're
looking to have under construction this
year we also have a couple smaller
projects including uh at Queen and farum
we're doing some intersection and
pedestrian improvements at that
intersection
so um that will be going it's in
currently in final design and we
anticipate that would go to construction
this year uh The Plum Street roundabout
has been mostly constructed but there
are some final um pavement restoration
that needs to be completed and signage
uh that wasn't able to get done before
the winter weather so that will be
completed in the spring as well um we
are also we just advertised and awarded
um traffic signal upgrades for uh
intersections along manner
Street um and yeah we just have a
various projects that were in more
preliminary design um and they are all
listed here um I if there are specific
questions about any of the projects I'm
happy to to answer them but we could try
and highlight different projects each
meeting just to give sort of an update
about what's going on with them this is
something a little bit different than
we've done before just so that people
have a better understanding of the
portfolio of work that's underway
throughout the city are there any
questions or comments at the commission
level regarding this
list any qu any quick questions or
comments from the public about this
list if if you would please come to the
podium indicate your name the Block in
which you live and what the item of
concern
is is the uh is the is there a green
light on
the there we go my name is Maria rhan
okay I see my name on this list and
you're in the you're in which block of
which ER the the block that I have
concerned the most is the one
on South and so as a matter of public
record for public meeting we're just
meeting the Block in which you reside
and then you can tell us about the
information okay it it it's not that I
reside there it happens so that I work
there I'm a caregiver like my sister is
also um my clients live in Garden Court
is this an agenda item excuse me is this
an item on the agenda yes so we'll get
we will get to this we will get to this
later on during the natural course of
the meeting okay great thank you yes I
just want to clarify not a problem now
we know you're here definitely thank
you're
welcome any other comments or questions
about the list of projects that have
been
presented he okay then we'll just go on
to the next item which is the action
agenda which we where we start with old
business the first item is item 47-22 24
considering the request of Celeste Sano
to restrict commercial vehicle parking
in the 400 block of par street is Miss s
present
is this is a followup update that's
correct sir can you do you want to take
it away Sergeant so this was uh this was
tabled from uh last year's last meeting
sir and Mr R was unavailable at that at
that time as well and we Ted until this
current meeting and since uh Mr Ron is
not present again um I would like to
make a motion that old business item
Agenda
47-20 24 be removed from the
agenda there's been a a motion second a
motion in a second and this reflects the
policy that if we don't have the ability
to
to question ask ask more information
about the situation at present there's
not the ability to adequately assess the
situation is there any further comment
from the committee commission
rather uh any comments from the
public hearing none there's a motion to
remove this from the
agenda all in favor I I any
opposed that motion carries thank you
very much the next item under old
business is item
49-22 24 considering the request of Kate
plank regarding pedestrian safety at
North Prince Street at West James Street
Miss Plank
present is this a followup than provide
an update okay and just identify
yourself so that people know who you are
sure thank you commission my name is Ben
Hogan I'm a public works engineer for
City of Lancaster just to provide an
update and a review of this item so this
was to provide additional pedestrian
protection at the intersection of North
Prince Street and West James Street on
the southern crosswalk of the
intersection it's a fast moving rightand
turn we're changing the signal phasing
to uh um prohibit right turns at certain
times which should improve safety for
pedestrians in the crosswalk we still
have that permit before pendot under
their review and have to get approval
from them before we can actually enact
those changes um we've procured the
equipment just waiting for that final
approval before we can install and move
forward with this so this will be an
administrative change
basically I believe so
yes that is correct the commission would
not need to take action so I think we
could um remove this from the agenda as
well would we would we continue to
update its progress or or no uh we could
um we can provide an update next meeting
I'm hoping it'll be finished by next
meeting so happy to speak on it then I
think that would be very good thank you
so does someone want to make a motion
that we that we remove this from the
uh from the
agenda as it's an administrative action
would like to make a motion that old
business agenda item 49202 4 be removed
from the agenda as will be an
administrative decision and updates will
be will be provided at the next DC
meeting there's a motion is there a
second I'll second is there any further
qu comment from the from the
commission from the
public hearing none all in favor I I I
any
opposed and um I do want to introduce uh
commissioner council members Janet Diaz
who's also a member of the commission we
had started the meeting by introducing
ourselves because there's new members
and about to change over so if you
wanted to say a word or
two I'm very happy to be here and um you
caught me because I'm a bit cold right
now but it's great to see um the
constituents coming out with their
concerns and that's what we're here for
to you know elaborate with you and make
sure that all your concerns are being
taken care
of thank you very much council
member so the next item on our agenda is
item 50- 2024 considering the request of
Katie berer of the Victor yoh
International Ballet Academy to make the
200 block of West Grant a oneway street
as the street is not large enough for
two vehicles to pass each Street making
drop off and pick up at time unsafe for
students along with other members of the
community Miss V are you
here anyone from Victor uh yoh
International Ballet
Academy are we reporting out on this one
Ben sure I can speak to it I believe it
was tabled last time um we did a
directionality assessment and a cursory
review of what it would mean to convert
that block to one-way traffic you should
have the uh sketch of directionality
before you for streets in that
neighborhood so West
Grant to the east of the 20000 Block
it's oneway Westbound and to the west of
the 200 block it's oneway
eastbound um this is a popular block for
walking and cycling in both directions
we have concerns that if we convert it
to one way way that would prohibit bike
travel in two directions and inhibit a
popular route that comes into downtown
um Additionally the blocks on either
adjacent side that are one way are
curbed on both sides so the difference
between this block is that there's
adequate room in parking areas to pull
off and yield to oncoming traffic
despite there not being enough room to
uh uh pass side by side on the roadway
so our recommendation based off of that
and a lack of Crash history at this
location was to uh keep it two-way and
uh not convert it to one-way
Direction and this is for the length
between Water Street and North mury
Street yes that's
correct are there any comments or
questions from the commission yeah this
is how this has arised uh several times
in the past about uh the 200 block of
West Grant and uh every time there it's
a proposal for One Way
conversion uh it always comes out that
uh there's there's always a number of
people that do not want to change it
they want to leave it two ways for
various
reasons
yeah so I I'm one of the people actually
who sometimes bites through that that
route um and would it be possible to
make it one way for cars and still B
traffic in both directions because well
there is parking there's uncurved
throughout it but the the like actual
intersection has buildings on both sides
and is pretty
narrow we could I think that could be a
consideration we did we have a few
similar contraflow bike Lanes throughout
the city it would just require
additional signage and pavement markings
and uh just based off of the lack of
Crash history we hadn't really
considered any changes to this block at
this time and more focus our priorities
elsewhere but I agree that cycling
traffic should remain in both directions
on that street whether it's converted to
one way or
not and at present it is it is and will
remain a two-way street
correct that's our
recommendation yeah I would just say
that there are
numerous locations throughout the city
that are similar to this um on Christian
Street we have a lot of a similar type
situation where um many portions are
two-way even though it's you know it's a
minimal RightWay width and a lot of the
intersections um have buildings and you
know things like that at the
intersection
so yeah for that reason I guess our
preference is to try and keep it two
way so we've heard Ben's assessment are
there any other comments or questions
from the commission itself
U any comments or questions from the
public regarding this
stretch um does one want to meet make a
motion to deny 50
2024 there's been a motion is there a
second I second motion and a second any
further
discussion hearing none all in
favor I any
opposed that motion carries thank you
very much thank you thanks Ben the next
item is on the old business business
action agenda is item 51 2024
considering the request of Kevin rals to
add a convex mirror to the intersection
of North Plum Street and Reynolds Avenue
is Mr rols
present was there further Mr Campbell um
I have received an email from uh Ben
Hogan requesting that agenda item
51-22 for the agenda item at hand be
taed until the next meeting which is not
something we Ty typically do as it has
already been tabled once um reason there
was a delay in notifying nearby
residents of this item and we would like
to give of additional time to arrange to
attend and I that doesn't seem
unreasonable does one want to make a
motion to that effect Mr you got a yes
so I guess the the issue was that we did
not recommend the convex mirror but we
did recommend removing some parking um
and that was raised as a con concerned
by some of the commission so um the idea
was that we would reach out to the
adjacent residents in that area to to
make sure they're aware of what we're
potentially proposing and they can
express any concerns related to that so
the yes there were I think we were
trying to get the letters translated to
make sure that they were accessible and
um there was some delay in that so we
just want to make sure there's adequate
time to notify those resence to allow
them the opportunity to attend okay or
provide comments in some form sounds
very reasonable to me does someone want
to make a motion concurring with that
recommendation yes sir I would like to
make a motion that agenda item 51-20 24
be tabled until the next draic
commission meeting is's a motion is
there a second second motion and second
any further
discussion any further comments from the
public um very very well all in favor I
I any opposed that motion carries that
will be tabled till next meeting thank
you
now we moving to the new business
portion of the action agenda and the
first item of the year is item 01 2025
considering the request of Lori alog of
South Central Transit Authority to
present additions and removals of rrta
bus stops throughout the city
Lori thank
you um this was uh started discussion at
the previous traffic Commission meeting
and um did not fully have all the
information together had to coordinate
with our director of operations and our
road supervisors um to provide the
information and then get the information
to the city um with um the actual
locations of the stops if they weren't
you know exactly identifiable and
um thankfully the city GIS Department
was able to take what data we had and
put it into a map I guess um you should
have that map there I'm not sure that
can be projected
oh well no it's not yet
projected Miss Gable did not receive a
map Mr Campbell she received um a chart
Source uh yes I did not send you the map
I'm sorry I I had assumed that Cindy's
office since they or the city since you
created it would would give it to you I
apologize do we have by any chance
readily enough at our fingertips that it
could be
shared is it useful to go through the
list and indicate the proposed changes
because not all stops our proposed
changes correct um the only ones that
are on the list that you received are
the ones um that this is the list for
additions which would be based on the
new uh routes that were
established um so there were six one two
three four five six six or seven new
stops um that we wanted that we had uh
worked through the city with um back in
December I believe and then the other
list of 40
or 41 are the ones um the locations that
we're looking um to remove because uh we
know longer provide service
there what what we're looking to see if
is if we if there's a way of being able
to pull up the map are you able to
yeah myy do you have access to your
email yes
just bear with us for a moment or two
yes I'm sorry I didn't coordinate that
but yes it is much easier to see on the
map um I only had the list uh because
our we do not have a GIS department so I
can individually look at them but our
data is not uh the best there we go
okay so do you want to talk us through
what we're seeing here
sure um if you can see the The Legend
there
um well they're supposed to the top
Legend is the orange
dots uh which you can kind of see are
proposed bus stop removals which like we
said there are um 40 of those and they
have on the map you can see they have a
number beside them that is um the uh
unique bus stop number within our
system um and then the next part of the
legend is it's red and yellow but you
kind of can't see that but the plus sign
there are the proposed uh bus stop
additions um so I mean I won't go
through all 40 of the list but um as I
said they are um for the the routes the
previous alignment of Route One um we no
longer cross Lemon Street so there are
several locations across lemon that we
would uh remove the bus stops
there um uh the one section of of James
Street um at mbery Mary Street and
Charlotte uh we do not provide service
along that section there and then um a
majority of the stops to be removed are
the um the old route
two um which went out to Park City and
then down down into the southeast so
these this portion here the majority um
of
these are the ones in the route two and
then there's um a few on the old uh
previous route five um North Lime Street
Park Avenue um Liberty and Plum shipping
and Ross up in that um that
area so again they are nicely ident
ified um on the map here um again with
the with the numbers there uh beside
them I do know that if if people had
have uh stayed AR bre of the
presentations and changes that that SCPA
has been making it's it's clear what the
logic is can you at a maybe 10,000 foot
level just describe very simply the
logic behind the reductions and or the
additions either to make it more make
more sense make it more timely more what
are the what are the key advantages to
the changes that you're
proposing um the the changes in the in
the routes we're looking at with um
public input and also
um just looking at at how the routes
went and making sure that um we hit some
some more of the spots that maybe we
hadn't before um so for the route the
new Route One the new route one is a
combination of um the route one and two
um so the southern part of the route one
which goes into the southeast down King
Street dolphin Chesapeake up Duke Street
um that um stays the same that southern
part of the the route two in the
Southeast it's the the difference is um
providing um a connection out this one
for example goes out to the um the uh
our Operation Center on Eric road which
is off of
dillerville and then coming across
Keller Avenue um which when the the
parking was available there for the
Amtrak station um there was a stop there
and then again passing by the staying by
the hospital and then um providing
service over to m
and then starting um starting the
southern Loop um so the again the route
part of the route to was caught up there
um do you know what kinds of changes
would be necessary either in terms of
signage or
uh indicating where those where the new
stops are and has that been worked out
with with uh either scta or with the
city on how that gets coordinated for
the new new stops um yes elimination of
the old stops as well um we hadn't
really talked about the elimination of
the old stops um that should just
involve where there are signs um
removing the sign and post um if it is
if it is on a uh separate post um I
didn't go through all of these some may
be on Telephone polls so it' be removing
removing the sign there
um and there were some questions that
there was at least one that wasn't
showing up um you know it didn't show up
on street view but it was so it probably
was not signed but we had it identified
as a stop so um I included it in there
because I wasn't sure how when this
started how they were officially
designated in the city so we had it a
stop in our system so we still wanted to
take that out so it was officially off
the Record um that way um so for the the
additional uh the new locations we did
have a meeting um with the city um in
December and went through each location
and identified um where we thought the
the stop could be and um preliminarily
um the city had agreed with that um so
we have there were temporary signs that
were put out at a couple locations
um there's been some problem with that
on ourn to get those temporary signs out
um but uh those six location seven
locations I'm sorry
um again you can see on the map they're
um mainly in the the
Northeast um going around with the new
uh route route
one so um the first the first one is um
the stop at directly across from LGH on
on Duke Street that would that's a new
stop but it's actually moving the stop
closer to Duke Street so it's not a
midblock um stop there um so that would
just be removing the the signage there
um and then that that location is also
one that um we need to coordinate with
the parking authority because there are
two two um uh they're not metered spaces
anymore um P parking spaces paid parking
spaces there um have you already had
those conversations or um I did contact
uh one person at the parking authority
and she told me to check with Cindy so I
have to make that loop back again
because I'm seeing I'm seeing in the
back the parking authority people are
saying no the loop is not yes yeah right
yeah because they told me to talk to you
we you told me to talk to them so yes I
have to coordinate on that um the next
location is at East Clay and at
Jefferson
Street um and that's at a location where
there already is uh no parking there in
the area so there is um no impact to on
street parking um Hamilton Hamilton
Street at Franklin
Street um there would be a stop again in
front of masi
but to not at the main entrance where
the big crosswalk is it would be um to
the left closer to um there's a small
crosswalk there um that seems to
be the more acceptable
location um obviously it's if you've
ever been there at school time it is
chaos all the time so but um that um we
checked with the drivers who've been
running that route right now now and
they feel that that is an is an okay
stop um location um uh North Franklin
Street at East
Walnut um which is a near side stop so
it's um south of Walnut Street and then
North Franklin Street at East Chestnut
again um on the southern side and then
uclid Avenue at Union Street in the far
Southwest I'm sorry in the far Southwest
yes
yes and that was because we
rerouted to go up uid to Fremont we used
to go the other way so and just out of
curiosity how are you planning to make
sure that the public understands the new
changes how will that be messaged and
communicated to the public and what kind
of a title frame are you looking
for um the stops as they are um were
identified have been put in our system
and so they are noted in um our our bus
finder um app if people use the their
phones and also online on the computer
system the the bus stops are there um
with these new locations we haven't
specifically um promoted them yet
because we don't have the full signs out
but we'll put notices um on on these
buses
um to identify the new stops
and and then um yeah for removing the
stops that goes with a part of the whole
process that we've been through with
identifying the the new routes um so we
haven't in our list of complaints um
that we've had I haven't I haven't seen
any that said if people have gone to the
wrong place and have been standing there
and and a bus never came like not
knowing that the route wasn't there
anymore um so hopefully some of the the
the root
information um although we do have still
some people riding saying they were
never aware of any of the changes but um
we think that that's been corrected
we've been trying to get a ride guide in
everyone's hand um responding to
complaints um and answering those direct
questions if people are questioning
where the stop is um because there are
some other routes that we haven't
outside of the city that we may need to
identify some locations that haven't
been so the the drivers um I mean it's
currently the policy outside the city
limits that the drivers um are allowed
you can flag stop wave down a bus so you
can be dropped off and picked up um
anywhere it doesn't have to be at
assigned location um so obviously but if
there are
some identifiable locations or
frequently used locations we would look
to um put signs up there um to identify
those locations is there anything else
you need to share with us uh before we
open it up to the commission I don't
think so okay thank you very much are
there any comments or questions from the
commission laor what's the go live date
I'm sorry what's the go live day for old
routes
removed uh old stops removed new stops
installed um we would do it as soon as
as soon as possible um that's one thing
I would need to coordinate with the city
my road supervisor has been telling me
in the past that the city always took
down and installed signs I don't know if
that's still the case we have staff to
do that we would coordinate with public
works yeah I think that yeah our
operations um sta have indicated that
they gen they do the signs and yeah they
okay so we would be sending this list to
them um I think the only outstanding
item is related to I believe that stops
along bu Canon where we have um put in
paper markings associated with the bus
stops that are now being removed and um
we have to figure out how how that's
going to be accommodated because I'm not
sure that's something that we can do in
house and I'm assuming that RTA can't do
that either which would involve
eradicating pavement markings and
putting down down new payment marking
correct we do not have those
capabilities we have discussions with
our TA on how we can how that can be
accommodated yes and that would be
something I would need to take to the
executive
director to coordinate um that we just
we had discussions as late as yesterday
afternoon um with Cindy and and Ben
about that item so that has not been
resolved yet so the request as stated is
to consider the request to present the
additions and removals I'm assuming
that's to seek approval of them as
well yes my understanding is to add or
remove any we need we uh the process is
to have um traffic commission um
approval of that so that they can on
your end be officially removed and then
we have them within our system as well
to know but more more so on on the
city's end within your records are there
other comments or questions I would just
ask is The List
complete
um um as I sent an email after I had
gotten the map realizing I had missed um
one at the Clipper Magazine
Stadium um and that was a remov correct
yes um and I don't know that there was
any actually any signage there but um we
have it as a stop in our system but the
Clipper the park and ride is no longer
there we don't service that so again I
didn't
know there are some that might not have
signage but we have them in our system
so I don't know how that you guys want
to still approve on you know take action
on them even though they're
not fully signed there or how you want
to do if it's not on a street a public
Street then we probably don't need to
okay take AC on mission level was this
Stadium yes yeah yeah that I don't think
you we don't have to worry about
that any other comments or questions um
yeah I was looking at the new stops and
at uh Hamilton and Franklin at least on
the street view it looks like there are
Flex post where I it looks like the bus
stop would go I would assume those would
need to be removed uh yes that is one
location that when we had the meeting
with the city um we talked about um
moving a couple of those delineators
leaving the the one at the end of the
striped area and since that's still no
parking allowing the the bus to pull in
there um and then be able to pull back
out great
thanks any other comments or questions
from the
commission any comments or questions
public please
just state your name in the block of
residents right yes so that you can hear
be heard in the microphone my name is
Carly Feldman and I'm a resident of the
600 block of Hamilton Street um I do not
own a car and if I need to travel
somewhere outside of my walking distance
I rely on RTA to get there um Raa
functioning effectively is extremely
important to me and my neighbors like me
I was a frequent user of the former
Route 2 uh the route that I believe was
altered the most by the route changes
that went into effect um and I have
experienced just a number of challenges
with the introduction of the new route
um which I believe could be remedied
with some marginal updates um
specifically um RTA to ensure that
operators service routes consistently
and follow posted schedules um at least
twice on the new route one I have
experienced operators skipping the
Northeast part of the route entirely um
re-entering the city heading sou and
continuing South straight to to Ule
Plaza um the route five bus at New
Holland and Franklin uh which was
scheduled actually for 7:15 a.m. this
morning was 10 minutes early and I think
that the recommendation is five minutes
that you get there five minutes early
for your stop and no service for the
scheduled 8:15 a.m. stop there this week
um additionally in regard to these other
changes um I would ask the RTA
reconsider how they handle the Eric road
service center stop on Route One
um I'm told that the stop was added so
that drivers could park up at the
station then ride down to Queen Street
um for customers needing to go all the
way up to the center you have to wait
for the gate to open they pull
in sometimes do some pick some folks up
turn around wait for the gate again um
my recommendation would be to um use the
bus stop that's right outside the gate
um it's on a culd toac it seems that
there's space enough to to turn around
in there um it's covered and then it
would also be accessible um when the
WellSpan Health Center opens it would be
accessible to the public using that stop
as well um I would also ask that you
declutter the stops on Route ones around
the Duke James and lime area there are
six stops that are currently proposed um
in that area um and no stops uh between
Shipman Street and Hamilton Street I
think there are two or three that are
slated there to be removed
um adding a stop at clay and Plum which
would correspond to stop 178 I think on
that map um uh would it's just around
the corner um uh and I have personally
seen folks who used the 178 regularly
flagging the bus down um at that
location um I would also request that
you amend the route one from masy to
downtown right now you have to to um you
travel on Reservoir past masi then you
make a right and then a left and the
Lehi Franklin intersection there is
really busy at school start and end
times um and a minor adjustment allowing
the route to continue straight up
Reservoir to Orange um would probably be
easier for operators they just need to
go straight through um and would only
move existing stops over one block um
thank you for your consideration uh
thank you very very much for the
commentary I do want to let people know
that this is to be reviewing an approval
of the stops and stop locations not the
roots so that's fine if I'm I see the
Lori is here if she's able to either
reach out to you or or touch base with
you to get some of that commentary and
it's it is recorded so uh but I do
believe she was requesting some changes
in the stops cor yes that's correct so I
like Lori are you able to respond to the
stop location changes that she
mention um not probably not on the spot
here I'd have to to look I mean the
stops the
um yeah I mean I can I can follow up I'm
I know that you have sent in other
comments as well um about the roots so
um I can get those and um see if there
are any changes we can make
and we can make any further adjustments
later as well
correct
sure
um there's another another oh I'm sorry
I didn't know there was somebody behind
me
go Keith risc lanter parking authority
um I guess we would want to obviously
still need to connect and make sure that
any of those spaces that could be taken
away are
um that we have reviewed it and reviewed
our deeds and everything else and we
since we haven't done that yet um I
would say we could you know if this
could be tabled that'd be
great if if this is table does this have
a major adverse effect to the roll
out um no I mean these are the stops
that we've identified so we we are
stopping near these locations um if we
need to modify that
um as we move forward we will um like I
said there were supposed to be um small
posts that say tempor that movable ones
that say bus stop there and we would um
put notice on on the buses as well um
still in this transition period from
starting the new rout and schedules um
from November 11th um the drivers have
been instructed um you
know to pick up people and drop off even
if it isn't um even in the city at at a
stop which has been the policy before
that within the city limits we want to
pick you up and drop you off at a stop
but since there is some shifting of the
the stops and there is a learning curve
for um the drivers you know we want to
make sure that we are picking up and
dropping off people and then get the
stops whenever they're you know these
additions or removals are approved um
again fully identify them to our driers
as well and then the customers very good
thank you are there other comments or
questions from the public
please okay my name is Nancy ya I live
at 18 northw Street and um I do not own
a
car I um so I rely on the buses and I
use buses and trains and um Uber also
so what I have noticed since um this new
schedule was was published in um or
started November 11th is that um there
is a lot of confusion among the users of
the bus so I'm just going to give you a
customer's um point of view and what
I've experienced and and heard in
general um the main problem is with the
signage so that the people don't know
where the stops are there's no way to
know where the
stops um are and I'm I'm dismayed that
this information about having signage
for both for the new stops and for the
changes wasn't done
before November 11th and it's January
and and um there's still um no markings
one of the places that I go is um I like
to shop at Wegman's and so previously on
the old schedule you got off at Long's
Park and it would just walk across and
through there through that shopping
center and then um there's now a bus
that goes through there but there's no
indication about where the buses stop
where they pick up there are there's a
huge apartment complex called The
Crossings and there is a bus that
there's supposed to be a bus stop for
people who live in in those um
buildings however those people have no
idea I know someone who lives in The
Crossings and he said how come I see
buses travel through here and I said
because that's part of the new route and
so
um that should have been made known to
them made known to The
Crossings um there should have been some
sign and I think you'd pick up you'd
pick up ridership but people have no
idea you know that there's even a stop
there and then
um so that's that's confusing I've also
had a problem with that bus let's see
which bus was that the number eight um
the number eight bus one time there were
people who were going to Park City there
only one stop for partk City there used
to be three um and we waited and waited
I was going to Wegman's Mo the all the
other passengers there were Pro 10 12 of
them were going to Park City um finally
it was a 2:00 bus at
2:30 someone came out a driver came out
and said oh well I'm your driver but I
don't have a
bus so we were loaded on a different bus
went to Eric Road um and picked up a new
bus uh it didn't go into Wegman's I just
got off at Longs Park but anyway it was
a total screw up so um and I've heard
other people other passengers who use
the bus um talk about the difficulties
that they've had um because mostly
because of the lack of
information um and so that's my um
that's that's my comments so I hope
those signs can be put up as soon as
possible including the old ones you know
people wait for the old at the old bus
stops um and um anyway that's that's my
story thank you for listening thank you
very very much and U miss alock you
never pronounce your name properly Al
alog is uh has heard all of your
comments as well I do ask a question is
there a plan for more advanced P wayf
finding in terms of um the signage not
just the locations of
the not just the locations of the of the
bus stops but how to get from one place
to another is is there a plan or are is
there any consideration for pathf
finding um not as of right
now
um I know that yes we we need to uh do a
better job of indicating where this the
stops are um in our in our ride guides
we have the routes identified but the
stops are not listed in here um I've
been talking with our director of
marketing to see if that's a location
that we can also identify the stops um
they as I said they are um on the
computer system um in the app they are
listed there and it tells you the name
of the Stop and the and the time when
the bus is supposed to be arriving um
and if if you log on at home but that
doesn't really do you any good unless
you're close to a stop that way but yes
of having um more maps to identify where
the stops are is something that we are
lacking okay very good are there any
other comments or questions from the
public is there a proposed U motion
regarding the
request yeah I'd like to make a motion
that we um approve these locations
contingent on review of all the
locations with LPA and staff one final
review um and yeah if there are any
modifications or anything that could be
brought back to the commission for an
approval just so we can get this moving
moving and completed yeah so there's a
motion is there a
second can I make a comment to the
motion
may I hear what this mccormic saying um
and I'm not saying you're
wrong I I have concerns that we're we're
approving a a a tentative stop
schedule without in in my opinion proper
citizenry input and the most important
conversation has to be had with
LPA right now the stops are they're
pretty
close but they're not definitive and I
hear what M mccormic saying if if there
are changes that need to be made it has
to come
back is it more prudent and I I I hear
what you're
saying I I don't see the reason why we
couldn't begin to move forward forward
with
changes especially signage and
notifications not everybody has access
to a cell phone or a
computer sometimes written formats are
the best whether that's an actual new
route posting on the bus stops
Etc is it more prudent to table until
the conversations have been made with
the major stakeholder being
LPA these are the absolute stops they're
good
they work for us they work for you and
the the finished list so to speak is
that brought before the commission for
the approval for the stops because right
now we're if we vote to approve these
are good but then we would have to come
back with potential amendments or
changes
to Yes uh so if I understand correctly
the the only new stop or moved stop that
that implicates an LPA issue is the
James and Duke Street one and correct
the potentially removed stock that I
heard a suggested that not be removed is
number 178 could we approve every other
stop every other addition that doesn't
impact LPA and every other removal uh
other than the one that perhaps um RTA
will consider keeping just so that we're
not duplicating work on those that might
change and we're not slowing down the
changes that can already happen my
understanding is that we can do it my
understanding is that we can do it that
way did LP get a chance to look at every
other stop and you only have an issue
with one is that
accurate there was only one stop that
had um meter parking spaces on it the
other stops were evaluated with Cindy
and her team
okay obviously we haven't had a chance
to review so I'll your word that if it's
only that one stop that has impact then
we're fine
okay any further
comments just do you want to make um do
we want to make an adjustment that says
with the exception
of stop 178 and stop is it 399 is that
one that
Duke um this stop at Duke the number is
uh 40 the stop at James and Duke is stop
number
40 oh
okay so
with do you want to amend it yeah I'll
I'll amend my motion to indicate that we
approve
um all the locations identified in the
packet except number 40 which we will
work out between between LPA and staff
and
RTA
um and approve all of the
deletions except for was it 178
178 except for
178 which we were also coordinate among
the staff so that's an amended
motion that's been made is there a
second I second there a motion in a
second is there any further discussion
qualifiers considerations to be
made hearing none all in favor I any
opposed
I one one one
opposition so the motion
carries um thank you very very much
please do work very closely not only
with LPA but with Cindy to follow up
with regarding anything else on on this
piece but thank you very much thank
you the next item is item
02 2025 consider the request of Jason
stalford of ekan development to add a
load Zone to either 2-8 South Duke
Street or 46 East King Street Mr staler
is Mr ster
present anyone from E development
present do we have enough information
about this request so Public Safety did
in fact
review um both of the proposed load
zones at either 2 to8 South duke or 46
East King Street it's the opinion of
Public Safety that neither one of those
locations are appropriate for a load
Zone and nor would we be able to
adequately accommodate those areas a
couple of the issues are are with LPA uh
probation and parole is in the area we
have distances from intersections we
have Seline issues um I personally
reviewed both of these load zones and I
personally denied both of those loow
zones that's simply for the board's
consideration
is there any further consideration is
this something that staff looked that as
well just very briefly that we looked at
it but
um yeah if the applicant isn't here I
wouldn't be inclin yeah and inclined to
make any take any action or anything and
there's already load zones in the area
so that that's another Factor we're
already currently have right in that in
that vicinity that's correct and Dustin
Hart from traffic um he also denied the
low zones um for similar reasons as
well so it seems that there's an option
of either tling it hoping that the
person might be able to come to the next
meeting or to deny it outright I would
be amenable to to hearing what Mr ekan
has or Mr stalford has to say about it
um my position isn't going to change
however my opinion is not going to
matter at the next meeting um but I
think the uh the appropriate call based
on past practice is to table um new new
business agenda item I'm formally making
a motion to table new business item
02-2020 until the next meeting and hopes
that Mr staler will be in
attendance Motion in a second any
further
[Music]
discussion hearing none all in favor I
any opposed that matter gets tabled the
next item in new business is item 03
2025 consider the request of Jack segro
of segro Lancaster Airport to address
issues with load zone changes at 358 to
360 North Queen Street Mr
serro very good welcome hello
everybody I just placing some names with
some Sergeant Grace J correct I'm sorry
I had meet talk very nice fell talked to
him on the phone I told me had some
problems with one of my family
members I was shocked to hear it I think
also uh Miss mccormic had some problems
with my
son no I have no issues no I did call
you but you never called me back okay uh
give you a little uh information on uh
sigr ner
airport we are the second
oldest business in
Lancaster the the uh Central Market is
the oldest we're the
second uh we're probably the we are the
oldest continuously run hair salon in
the United States we go back to
1850 uh
I'm here because
uh we had some uh intersection
daylighting installed in front of our
hair styling salon and took out one of
our uh there's a picture of it now uh
took out one of it our parking
spaces uh and that was right before
Thanksgiving so we decided to take some
numbers of some people that came down to
to our par stying
Salon Thanksgiving
week
268 people use the parking
meters for the week and we're open four
and a half days a week Christmas
week there was 391 people Ed the parking
meters and New Year's week there was 289
people used the parking meters in
between time
there was 177 people used the parking
garage for the week Christmas week there
was 31 people used the parking garage
and New Year's week there was exactly
10 and we just Saed our customers for a
short period let me give in information
on
uh on Queen Street the 300 block of
North Queen Street if you Google it it
says it's
the uh it's the block the shop in
Lancaster and I believe they're right I
think our next competitor is probably
Park City
no uh we have
100 one businesses on the
block how did how did 1001 Business get
on the
Block we have 31 businesses on the
street
and we
have building characters which has 70
plus
vendors but the main entrance is on
Queen
Street a lot of
traffic also we
have
128 apartments on the
street it's 72 with a new building that
was just uh built across the street from
us and
56 on top of the
businesses and
uh on top of the business is on the Main
Street on Queen Street there's
also one Airbnb on the
Block there's three restaurants and
possibly fourth coming on the Block and
Bader on the corner of the next
block and there's uh
let's
see oh there's
uh three dogs six cats and one St cat
lives on the
street uh before this
it before this intersection daylighting
started I was going to uh try to get our
loading zone extended and then this hit
and
uh it threw us for a loop because it is
causing
problems I have I am the uh I was the
president and I am the on the board of
the Lancaster County Sports Hall of Fame
so I get a lot of athletes and athletes
become crippled earlier in life so we do
have a lot of handicap and
disability people that uh come to our
business on the men's side the women's
side not so much the men's side is
pretty there's a lot of canes and
Walkers we have a ramp to get in we have
17 electric scooters that come in
so everybody knows we take handicapped
customers and with with the uh shortage
of a loading
zone uh for the whole
block uh it it just it's it's bogging us
down Uber's coming
in uh everybody's ordering out door Dash
uses it trucks all day long use it and
we try to use it you know not but we
don't say anything about anybody else
using it it's there for
everybody
so all the business on Queen Street we
should be trying to get people in there
should be better parking for these
people and uh you know we we shouldn't
discourage people uh we we're trying to
all make a money and the people on on
the 300 block had a bad Christmas season
the economy's down
uh but our customers do multi- buying on
the street when they come in for a
haircut they usually go to a restaurant
or they go to get candy or they go to
the pickle shop and buy uh pickles and
uh cheese and but they're all all of our
customers usually buy something else on
the Block so our people are spending a
lot of
money so in summary what I'm going to
requesting is our loading zone from two
spaces to
three
because and we have a back parking lot
also which is used too but I didn't put
those figures in our in our list so we
draw a lot of people and we bring a lot
of people to town we try to service them
you know the best we can but we have to
have some cooperation from the city
also and currently your your current
loading spaces are on North queen or on
Lemon we're pardon me sir the current
loading spaces that you say you have is
on Queen Street yes
sir has Ben a
look I mean yeah Sergeant jurus has
looked at it we have looked at it I
guess what happened was when um there
was a loading Zone that went directly up
to the crosswalk um so the in this
picture there's a pole on the right that
has the loading zone sign when we right
there's the pole and then you can see
the loading zone sign on it when we
installed the bike Lanes on Lemon Street
we daylighted that intersection
providing the 20 ft of um distance from
the crosswalk that you know we've done
at all the
intersections um this reduced their
loading zone from basically one parking
SP or two parking spaces to
one um it wasn't oversight on our part
not to notify
um notify them about this
reduction um and we did
speak you know I guess with your son
right and the impression that I get is
that the load loading zone is used as
parking for the handicap
customers we don't want to call them
handicap yeah no I'm just kidding that
need assistance or otherwise I offered
to
um you know rather than have because
that's not the intent of the loading
zone is to provide for parking um for
someone um I offered to provide an
accessible parking space which you know
would allow um people with placards to
be able to park there um they weren't
interested in that option I didn't hear
about that
um so yeah I guess we're we're just
trying to balance like
the the um what the true definition of a
loading zone is and um you know the
guidance is that it's a 20 minute
loading and unloading it's not to be
used for parking for you know people to
visit businesses or do those other
things
so um I guess I had not heard about
about the request to increase it to
three
spaces I think the request was to sort
of get back what they initially had but
in light of knowing what the what it's
being used at as we um we not I mean if
you see us you're you're on Google Maps
and you see that you can see we go out
and help people into the facility we
take them out we we put them in their
car we strap their seat Bel on I mean we
do everything for people you know even
when when they have a driver we do that
make sure they're you
know and we've always done it that's
that's why we been in business all this
time
yeah so if I could just pick it back on
M McCormick's comments um Mr cro you and
I spoke on the phone and I did in fact
offer you that the persons with a
disability parking area I I I didn't
remember it because I was I was upset
about this whole thing so maybe I didn't
hear it you know okay so if you notice
up on the scen
um that that's the load Zone
application and under item number six a
load zone is designated as any vehicle
is in a process of AC loading or
unloading a property May utilize a load
Zone applica does not reserve the load
zone for exclusive use as you stated in
your presentation as you stated in your
emails the load zone is in fact being
used for your
customers with disabilities so they have
easier access to to your hair salon is
that accurate yes so that having been
said that the purpose that your
customers are using a load zone for is
not in fact what a load zone is supposed
to be used
for backtrack probably 40 or 50 years
that low Zone should have never been
installed where it was installed it was
in violation of city
ordinance being too close to the
crosswalk and or too close to the
intersection so we're either 20 ft from
a crosswalk or 30 Fe from an
intersection the sign should have never
been installed that far north on Queen
Street to begin
with present day load Zone's been
reduced the the purposes based on your
statements for that load Zone I I am
inclined to deny that request because
it's not in fact being used for its
intended purposes which is the loading
and unloading of goods not persons the
appropriate step would be to give
you not give you but install a
designated person's with disability
parking space for your customers to use
with the caveat that those spaces are
not for the exclusive use of your
customers realizing of course in the
Commonwealth Pennsylvania that anybody
with a plaer or persons with the
disability license plate May in fact
occupy that
spot okay can you go over that one more
time sure okay which
part uh the last part sure so the person
so the load Zone as it stands right now
is not being used for its intended
purpose right it's not fact for the use
of loading and unloading of goods to
your business it's in fact being used
for the loading and unloading of persons
to your business based on your statement
and your emails this is for your your
some of your clientele that has disc
disabilities the appropriate thing would
be to remove the load Zone in its
entirety and replace it with a person's
with disability parking
space that having been said if in fact
we do install that
space realizing that anybody not
necessarily for the exclusive use of
your customers if they have a placard or
if persons with disability license plate
May occupy that parking space and doing
so may in fact negate your customers
from using that space I'm going to go
one step further on the east side of
Lemon Street oh I'm sorry on the east
side of Queen Street so the first block
of East Lemon Street if not already
installed there will be a load Zone
installed right across from your
business I realize it's not as close as
curbside but there is place but also
understand that that load Zone can't be
for based on your own statements for
your clientele to come in receive a
haircut and go shopping that's not the
intended use of a load Zone well they do
use it to go shopping on the Block and
and they can't that that's not they
can't do that they may not no how about
the delivery
trucks so delivery trucks that that's
the intended use of the load zone for
the the loading and unloading of goods
to a business and 70% of the load of the
uh is used by utility uh trucks all day
long there if you if you Google it
you'll see they're dri they're dropping
off at the badier they're dropping off
at all the restaurants the three
restaurants and the fourth one's coming
and uh it's just Uber uses it um door
Dash uses it Amazon uses it uh all those
are ker water uses it I mean those those
are all apprpriate uses of the load Zone
those are absolutely appropriate uses
where where where where would they go
then I I don't have that answer I I'll
be honest with you I haven't looked that
far ahead I'm sure we could have
discussions with Mr McCormick Mr Hogan
uh Mr RIS about where we could
potentially reload locate a loading zone
on that block for its actual intended
purpose which is the loading and
unloading of goods doesn't solve your
issue however I think the appropriate in
my mind the appropriate step is to deny
the request of the extension of the low
Zone in fact I don't believe the low
Zone should be used and allowed to be
used for the for your
customers but that's going to kill
us it's it's going to be knife in our
heart seriously well please understand
that that's certainly not my intent
pardon me that's certainly not my intent
do harm to yourself or your business or
your clients I mean we have that we have
those disability guys you know may maybe
a a loading zone of one spot and a and
and a disability spot might
be might be a good
fit well and then I'm looking at the
actual agenda which is considered
request of Jack SE seag lanter airport
to address issues with the low zone
changes at 358 to
360 I think we've Vally addressed those
issues and I'm not sure if it's if it's
appropriate to bring before the board an
action to take about the existing low
Zone I will leave that up to discussion
with my fellow board
members right now what they what it is
is this intersection daylighting
personally I've had myself and my family
members and we've been checking the
streets on North Queen Street of
crosswalks actually Queen and lemon is
one of the least walk crosswalks in the
city and you know what the first one
came out to
be does anyone have an idea no the one
the last one behind the train train
station which is hard to believe you
think people getting off of trains would
cross that it's hardly ever used it's
it's it's truly
unbelievable I'm a numbers guy so I you
know I I like to you know play around
with numbers and you know
so so it sounds to me that one of the
things that you might want to consider
is either withdrawing your request and
working with staff to see if there's a
way that it a a handicap and a load Zone
space might be afforded or just a
handicap
Zone well some someplace on the Block
there's going to be need for uh a load
Zone I mean we get we get we we get
loads every day and that would be the
reason to work with staff to figure out
how do you address both needs yeah I'll
work with anybody is that something that
makes sense
sure I'm volunteering I'm volunteering U
Ben again
Ben Ben and I had
some huh
CH I believe there was a load Block in
front of
characters that that he gave up I'm not
sure and I honestly believe that's
probably the best base for a loading
zone on that block Marty gave it up
though I believe which would be mid
Block in the 300 block yeah um and and
again we we're tasking for Mr Hogan with
with with yet another task but I I think
that's the the appropriate I don't
remember one day take a look at the 300
block make a determination on the Block
40 years Lo Zone best place if if it was
there was one but the bottom line is
what exists now number one it should
exist and under ordinance really can't
exist
corre oh by the way looking at loading
zones here's another one right in front
of the state
store that's the second oldest state
store in the state of Pennsylvania and
never realize that and
they're you knew
it all right am I uh done well Mr I
think the appropriate question asked um
okay we we have two options one we can
make a motion to vote on this or you can
make a request to the board to remove
withdraw your request and work and then
work with the city to and staff to try
to make a an appropriate come up with an
appropriate solution for your
issues and I'm not pushing you one way
or the other I'm just letting you know
that's probably what we're going to do
here in a minute or two well I'm sure if
I come back it's going to be the same
thing because you're you're pretty said
on think the option in my mind is yeah
either we're leaving the one space as a
loading zone or we're making it an
accessible parking space we cannot
accommodate a loading zone and an
accessible parking space there because
the accessible space would need to be on
the Northern side so and we're not going
to put a loading zone you know in the in
between parked cars there so then I
think you know then it goes back to the
loading zone would probably be more you
know in the mid block location orj to a
driveway or some other location where
there's more room to pull in and out you
know without impacting parking as
much my heart's broken believe me that
that really uh really hurts our
business I can't tell you what to do
because um I'm uh can't think straight
right
now would you so we can so I have to sit
down and talk to Ben for come up with
something and bring it back to the
meeting I
will but uh are you willing then to
withdraw the current request knowing
that excuse me I'm sorry are you willing
to withdraw the current request knowing
that you can bring it back I guess
that's what I have to do all right thank
you very much thank
you do we need to take any action if
he's
withdra
okay thank thank you very much and we
we're looking forward to your proposal
the next action item is item 04 2025
considering the request of Sarah and
Drew wiard to Grant a permit parking
exemption for 13 South an
Street uh good afternoon commission my
name is Sarah Wingard speaking on behalf
of me and my husband Andrew
Wingard um I know there's not a
precedent for this so I thank you for
hearing my request I purchased 13 South
an Street in February of 2023 with the
hope of Renning out one of the units
affordably while living in the second
one I'm a social worker in the city at
church World Service and be have become
passionate about affordable housing in
Lancaster I recently however got married
and my husband is fostering was
fostering uh through Lancaster Children
and Youth and then I followed um to be
um certified as well and we are the
parents of a 16-year-old Foster son
we live in the second unit of a the two
unit home I own he works as a high
school teacher outside of the city um
but because of the rule of having one
parking pass per unit we're only able to
have um one for our family though it's
our primary residence and I own the
property we were hoping to request an
exception for us to have two parking
passes for our block um recently there
has been plenty of parking and there's
often three three or more open spots
When I Look to Park we're hoping to
continue to foster children through
Lancaster County C starting this summer
and it's difficult to park far away from
your house when you have small
children um the rule states there's no
more than two residential parking
permits that can be issued per for a
single family dwelling um we could have
purchased a single family dwelling and
had two permits but chose to purchase a
two unit in order to provide affordable
housing to someone or persons in
Lancaster and we currently rent to two
people coming out of recovery here in
Lancaster well below market value I hope
you will consider our request to get a
second permit for our apartment thank
you very much Miss lingard um do do you
want to stay up here in case there are
some questions
so Council are there questions or
comments regarding the
request I hate to do it but I think I'd
almost want to punt this to LPA get
their get their input I called them they
told me to come
here I I just wanted to ask if there's
any off street parking at here no off
street parking pretty much in the whole
block yeah
yeah
um sergeant if you were if you were
punting to LPA what question would you
have have LPA try to
answer I I would like to
know if theyve made exemptions in the
past if my family memory serves they
have and maybe the criteria for granting
those
exemptions and we're already dealing
with that really crowded horrible area
right there and in east end with the
rppp issue to begin with right and my my
initial thought it is a denial because
of
those compounding issues that are
specifically related to that
area you know quite frankly
understanding your issue is I I
completely get it
um I'm not sure if Larry is prepared to
speak or not I I was gonna defer to
Keith but um I believe I believe the
exemptions are related to um multif
family where there where we are allowing
up to five permits per facility so if
there were five units and only four
permits were applied for then we would
allow an exception that someone could
get a second permit contingent someone
contingent on the fact until yeah
someone else that was eligible applied
and then they would lose that permit um
I believe that's the only exemptions
that we've actually right sort of added
to the process that they currently allow
does that exemption only apply for four
units entire or for any multiple unit
well it's any multi-unit so any for a
multi-unit they are allowed one permit
per unit so in this case units and they
get one permit but there's a
three-bedroom house across from our our
street that just sold that has you know
it's a single dwelling so it has two
permits but like we chose yeah so it's I
don't know I could have bought a normal
house but I chose yeah this is what I
chose so what are our
options I mean I think in light of you
know the the moratoriums that we've had
on permit parking the you know the
concessions that we've asked other
people especially on an Street you know
people wanted to add r p on an Street
and we've asked them to wait I don't
know that you know and they asked
for different solutions to how they
could um have additional parking and
we've asked them to wait I don't know
that it would be
um Equitable to to Grant an extra permit
for this application this particular
site is it within the
proposed um pilot area or is it just
adjacent because it's very close to the
I mean it's in the general area of you
know where an street is right the permit
parking is it currently exists
obviously I'll be hon I'm not sure it's
either in the area or it's just one
block north of the area right one of the
two is the one block north
permitted it's no so it's not correct
what I mean is your block Sor would be
one block north of the proposed
permanent area which I understand okay
it's it's the efforts we're making to in
over a short amount of time overhaul the
RPP program make it more available and
or less available more available where
there's greater need less available
where there's less need sure I totally
understand that's
fine and is there is there rppp on the
other side of the block as well is it
always both sides both sides of St
permit
so what I'm hearing is that this is an
except this request is for an exception
that's not different than other
exceptions that people have made before
sure um and even though it may be
inconvenient we we'd be asking you to to
be patient and or try to enlist being
part of the a pilot as that's being
defined um sure and um hopefully within
then the next year year or so will have
much greater clarity about how the RPP
zones can be either expanded or changed
as necessary okay thank
you is that sufficient do we need to
take action then I I believe we do I do
yeah so um I would make a motion that
agenda item
04202 be
denied um obviously in light of the
proposed uh impendent changes yeah it's
been a motion is there a second
second is there any further
discussion all in favor I I any oppos
thank you the motion carries sorry
hopefully you'll be able to be patient
enough and be able to benefit from the
changes that are being made over the
course of the next year no thank you so
much next we get to our consent agenda
there are three items but there's one of
the items is one where M Ron had asked
to speak earlier yeah so let's take the
first two consent agenda items first
because we usually we can just get them
out of the way and then we'll reach out
for the third one so I would like to
make a motion that consent agenda item
05-22 five and 06
d202 be approved as posted there's been
a motion second and a second Is there
further disc
discussion hearing none all in favor I I
I any opposed that motion carries so the
next item is item 07 2025 the following
conditional temporary parking permits
have been issued by LPA right one of
them being Maria rolon who is caregiver
for two clients at 9 and 12 Garden
cour hello this is leet
Floyd I
yes you're one of the first the first
one yes okay uh I've been living here
for the past nine month caring for my
sister who suffer a stroke and we've
been through quite some
challenges
from having my vehicle towed at a Garden
Court after they gave me a permit to be
there to having four tickets so
far so
right now I'm spending $60 a month to
find somewhere to
park
and I would like for you to
consider some kind of change that we
caregivers will have a break like maybe
just one fee per year for parking is
very challenging to park
there if you're not there early you
might as well go around in circles all
night because there's that many people
there so
um Can someone propose an idea of how we
caregivers can have some kind of break
can I from spending $60 a month sorry I
would like to share something because we
both are in the same situation at the
same place we both had issues with not
be able to Grant they Haven grant us a
space for all caregivers because there's
a a big group in that Garden Court that
need help and we are talking see
speaking on behalf of the other
caregivers we all go through the same
situation the streets around accept and
Street has a 2hour limit of permit so
meaning the other day I have a 25
ticket for caring for one of my
clients I have one client cannot walk so
meaning that I have to go around pick up
my car go pick him up take him to the um
whatever situation wherever he has to go
then come back there's no space for me
meaning that I have to go around 15 20
minutes in order for me to get a parking
space because the only way we can park
is on an Street
both side but because it's so limited we
end up going the 2hour permit and every
single time we have to interrupt our
work ER time or schedule because we have
to move that car somewhere else before
that that two hour limit you
see so uh please clarify for me what has
been what has been granted
here is uh temporary parking permits for
both of you for each of you yes okay but
that does not address your problem in
terms of the amount no because we have
to come down here to purchase that um
that permit but if we we want to propose
that if we can do this fee once a year
instead of going every month every month
or to do this m yeah I don't think just
just add some clarification um so miss
Floyd yes sir M Ron yes M
sea not here she's no she's not here all
the two of you ladies you have been
granted the parking permits the
caregiver permits they have been granted
to you okay you simply have not received
them yet okay and that's what this
meeting
formalizes that those have been granted
to you you simply need to retrieve them
and you will be you'll be good to go
you'll be allowed to park there
realize I can't guarantee you that a
parking space is going to be available
for
you oh we know that but it'll be easier
to find but at least if there's a space
there we don't have to be worrying about
that we have to change this car correct
every two hours for we don't so we don't
get penalized right and that's that's
what the per the purpose of these
permits being granted to you so you can
go
there and without a repercussion of a
ticket right and how long does uh we up
it every month no and and and what is
how long this ticket lasts once a year
once a year what is the
fee I don't have that answer
[Music]
where do they get the permits where you
would come down to 30 West
or sorry about that because I know my
voice carries um how long is the
caretaker permit good for the caraker
permit's good for that remainder of that
year it's almost like an RPP you're
getting that parking space for for one
year as an additional caregiver permit
for that for that space and so you'd
come to Lancaster parking authority 30
West Orange um we need to get your
vehicle information register
everything and it's the cost I believe
it's either 20 or 30 for the year and
that's what you pay and then we do
everything off your license plate okay
awesome
awesome we'll be there tomorrow all
right I'll be and the same applies to
miss SE supp as well okay okay thank you
so much take
my apologies for
mispronunciation that's okay no
problem and sorry for misunderstanding
based on the information that we've just
heard I would like to make a motion to
approve consent agenda item
07202 as well as
08-20
25 there's been a motion is there a
second second motion and second and for
the com
all in
favor any opposed both carry thank you
so much thank you
Janet you're very welcome thank you sir
is there any any additional
business's oh he he included seven an in
this
motion any additional business no sir if
not um I'd like to bring this meeting to
a close if someone wants to make a
motion to close the meeting make a
motion
to I would like to second that motion
okay motion and seconded all in favor I
the meeting has been adjured thank you
very very
much I
[Music]
your